Guide to the Yevgeny Yevtushenko Papers M1088
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Political Papers, Series 2.
  Political Papers include drafts and copies of letters written to significant political figures including Brezhnev, Gorbachev, Shevardnadze, and Yeltsin, in addition to letters to the Central Committee of the Communist Party and other political organizations. It also includes correspondence and transcripts of official discussions of a number of his works, materials related to Yevtushenko's election as People's Deputy from Khar'kov, and papers related to his participation in the organizations Memorial and Pamiat. Papers from the archive of the Union of Soviet Writers include personal forms of Pasternak, Tvardovskii, Zabolotskii, and Zoshchenko, and correspondence between Pasternak and Markov.
  - Letters to General Secretaries: Brezhnev, Andropov, Chernenko (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Fax copy of a typed and signed letter to Brezhnev concerning publication of Yevtushenko's books and restriction on his performances, 1969 Apr 7. Copy of typed letter to Brezhnev and the Politburo concerning censorship, n.d. Copy of a typed letter to Brezhnev concerning Taganka Theater, signed by Yevtushenko, Vosnesenskii, and Denisov, n.d. Fragment of a copy of typed letter to Andropov concerning Glavlit, n.d. Copy of typed and signed letter to Chernenko concerning an event sponsored by Taganka Theater in memory of Vysotski, n.d.
    Andropov, Iurii; Chernenko,; Brezhnev, Leonid
  - Correspondence with Shevarnadze (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Includes: Letter from Yevtushenko to Shevarnadze (as Minister of Foreign Affairs) concerning Yevtushenko's recent trip to Brazil, n.d.; Shevarnadze's reply to Yevtushenko's Brazil letter, 3 pg. TMsS, 1987 June 6. Letter from Yevtushenko asking Shevarnadze (as president of Georgia) to help Nelli Betashvili acquire an apartment in Tblisi, n.d. Three telegrams from Shevarnadze to Yevtushenko.
    Shevarnadze, Eduard
  - Letters to Gorbachev (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Includes: Copy of letter to Gorbachev concerning registration of "Memorial", signed by Yevtushenko and others, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev concerning Pasternak house museum, signed by Yevtushenko and about 10 others, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko on behalf of Nika Turbina, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko concerning an international evening of poetry to be held in the USSR, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko thanking Gorbachev for his attention to matters of Pasternak, Turbina, and the evening of poetry, and complaining about Glavlit's policies, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko concerning the censure of an article, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko concerning Norman Mailer's letter to Gorbachev and requesting the release of poetess Irina Ratushinskaia, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from A. Askol'dov concerning his expulsion from the Party, 1987 Jan 20. Annotated typescript of a letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko requesting that the PEN-club be exempt from taxes, n.d. Copy of letter to Gorbachev from Yevtushenko concerning his speech at the Russian Writer's Congress, n.d.
    Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich
  - Letters to Yeltsin (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Includes: Handwritten draft and copies of letter to Yeltsin (as first Secretary of the Moscow Committee) from Yevtushenko including a number of suggestions for Moscow, n.d. Printed out draft of letter to Yeltsin (as President), Chernomyrdin, Chubais, Nemtsov, and Sysuev from Yevtushenko concerning Okudzhava, censureship, and Sokolov's widow, n.d. Letter to Yeltsin and Putin from Yevtushenko concerning the situation in Georgia and Abkhazia.
    Yeltsin, Boris Nikolaevich
  - Letters to the TsK KPSS (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Includes copies of letters from Yevtushenko to members of the Central Committee concerning attempts to found the new journal "Masterskaia," an International Festival of Poetry initiative, "Melodia" and Yevtushenko's record with Gleb Mai, censureship, the Taganka Theater, suggestions for the Writer's Union, Andrei Petrovich Gavrilov, foundation of a Union of Photographers, Glavlit. Copy of letter from S.M. Mikhailovskii concerning a memorial at "Drobitskii Yar."
    Demichev, P.N.; Central Committee; Iakovlev, Aleksandr; Dolgov, K.M.; Suslov, M.A.; Shauro, Vasilii Filimonovich
  - Fragments of letters to the TsK KPSS (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes a fragment of a letter to the Moscow City Committee concerning Bulat Okudzhava.
    Okudzhava, Bulat; Central Committee
  - Miscellaneous Letters to Officials (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Letters cover topics including: publication of "Mama i neitronnaia bomba"; honorarium payments to writers; "Iagodnye mesta"; a new journal for young writers called "Masterskaia"; "Novye vybory starymi metodami?"; an apartment for his mother; land in Peredelkino; censorship; the right of Crimean Tartars to live on the land of their fathers; on behalf of the mother of Neizvestnyi - Bella Abramovna Dizhur, Farid Kaiumi and his wife Elena Kaiumi, and Simon Franklin; and "Dvadtsatyi vek."
    Novyi Mir
  - Letters on behalf of others: Betashvili, Idu Nudel, Svetov (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of a letter from Yevtushenko concerning the release of Idu Nudel at the request of actress Jane Fonda.
    Fonda, Jane; Nudel, Idu; Svetov; Betashvili, Dzhumber
  - Fragments of letters (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Includes manuscripts and typescripts. Includes a page entitled "Otvetstvennost'" by Andrei Voznesenskii.
    Voznesenskīĭ, Andreĭ
  - Letters to Yevtushenko (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Typed and signed letter on U.S. Senate letterhead from William S. Cohen, 1984 Mar 19. Holiday card from the President of the Republic of the Philippines and Mrs. Ferdinand E. Marcos.
    Cohen, William S.; Gorostiza, Carlos; Marcos, Ferdinand; Stoessel, Walter John
  - Concerning the poem "Fuku" [letters, reviews] (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Reviewers include Evgenii Sidorov, Egor Isaev, Margarita Aliger, A. Mezhirov, Rasul Gamzatov, Vladimir Sokolov, L. Anninskii, Stanislav Lesnevskii, Iu. Nagabin, G. Semenov, Chingiz Aitmatov, among others.
  - Redaktsiia Zhurnala "Novyi Mir": Stenogramma: zasedaniia redkollegii po obsuzhdeniiu poemy Y. Yevtushenko "Fuku,", 1985 July 31 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Photocopy of typescript, 20 p., 1985.
  - Stenogramma: Seminara pod rukovodstvom tov. Zakharchenko Po obsuzhdeniiu stikhov poeta Y. Yevtushenko, 1955 April 1 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Discussion of the poems of Yevtushenko, under the leadership of Comrade Zakharchenko.
  - Postanovlenie Sekretariata Soiuz Pisatelei, 1955 - 1956 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    1955 May 25 - transfer Yevtushenko from candidate to member of the Writer's Union. 1956 Apr 27 - censure
  - Vystuplenie na plenume pravleniia soiuza pisatelei SSSR, 1963 Mar. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Iz stenogrammy: obsuzhdenie Soiuz Pisatelei "Avtobiografii", 1963 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Writer's Union discussion of "Autobiography."
  - Concerning "Babii Iar" and Shostakovich's 13th Symphony, 1963 - 1964 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Includes: copy of translated article by V. Kuptsov entitled "Yevtushenko dolzhen pererabotat' stikhotvorenie 13-ia simfoniia Shostakovich sniata s programmy," 1 p., 1963 Jan 12; copy of letter to the Central Committee from Polikarpov and Snastin, 2 p., 1963 [?] Sept. 30; 2 copies of letter to Central Committee from Snastin, Kukharskii, and Mikhailova, 2 p., 1963 May 15; 2 copies of letter to the Central Committee from T. Khrennikov of the Composer's Union, 1963 Feb. 21; 2 copies of letter to Il'ichev "O trinadtsatoi simfonii D. Shostakovicha", 3 p. plus handwritten notes, 1963 Mar. 24.
  - Soiuz Pisatelei SSSR: Postanovlenie Sekretariata [travel to Italy denied], 1964 Jan. 20 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Letter from KGB to TsKPSS, 1964 July 6 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Copy of fax, 3 p. [Yevtushenko's list #8]
    Semichastnyi, V.
  - Letter from KGB to TsKPSS, 1966 Jan. 15 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Two copies of faxcopy of letter, 3 p.; also multiple copies of an illegal leaflet in defense of Yevtushenko that was in the KGB archives.
  - Letter to TsKPSS concerning Yevtushenko, 1966 Nov. 15 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Copy of typescript, 2 p. [Yevtushenko's list #9]
    Barabash, Iu.; Melent'ev, Iu.
  - Letter of A. Solzhenitsyn to All - Union Congress of Soviet Writers, 1967 May 16 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    TMsS, 2 p., 1967 May 16.
    Solzhenitsyn, Aleksander
  - Concerning "Severnaia Nadbavka", 1977 May (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Typescript, 2 p. [Yevtushenko's list #42]
    Beliaev, A.; Romanov
  - "Declaration of Three" to Worlds Writers, Appeals for Liberty of Nicaragua: Yevtushenko, Allen Ginsberg, Ernesto Cardenal, 1982 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Copy, unsigned.
    Cardenal, Ernesto; Ginsberg, Allen
  - Correspondence with S. Kalistratova and l. Bogoraz about general amnesty, 1986 - 1987 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Kalistratova, S; Bogoraz, I.
  - Correspondence of I.L. Itkin concerning 1987 March 18 Yevtushenko performance (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Itkin, Il'ia Lazarevich
  - Kompartiia Izrailia torpediruet usiliia po priezdu v Izrail' Sovetskogo poeta Yevtushenko: [newspaper article], 1987 Dec. 18 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Printed in newspaper "Davar", 1987 Dec. 18
  - Signed poem by Konstantin Pomerantsev, 1988 Feb. 18 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    "Ne Gorbachev stranoiu pravit..."
    Pomerantsev, Konstantin
  - Rech' na S'ezde Sovetov 1 iiunia, 1988 June 1 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - "Antitezis": Newsletter, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Otchet chlena nezavisimoi komissii Lel' Evgeniia Ivanovicha, 1989 May (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Speech: Soiuz Pisatelei, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    "Nedavno, v odnoi iz televizionnikh program bylo privedeno pis'mo devushek iz Cheboksar..."
  - Khar'kov elections: letters to Yevtushenko, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Khar'kov elections: Poems by Others, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Khar'kov elections: Pochemu Ia vybral Khar'kov, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Khar'kov elections: Gruppy poderzhki kandidata E.A. Yevtushenko, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    Press releases concerning Yevtushenko's program, etc.
  - Khar'kov elections: Yevtushenko biographies, programs, etc., 1989 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Khar'kov elections: Clippings, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    Vechernii Kharkiv: 1989 Mar 25
  - Khar'kov elections: other candidates, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    Vitalii A. Korotich, Sergei Borisovich Stankevich
  - Narodnyi Deputat SSSR: miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes: Yevtushenko letterhead; chernovik deputatskogo zaiavlenie (draft of deputy declaration), n.d.; publication entitled "K vyboram narodnykh deputatov SSSR po Leninskomu territorial'no-izbiratel'nomu okrugu No. 1 goroda Moskvy."
  - Konstitutsiia (osnovnoi zakon) Soiuza Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Publication.
  - Ukaz (Presidential Decree), 1991 Aug. 19 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Handout of decree by Boris Yeltsin, President of RSFSR, 1991 Aug 19, 1pm.
  - Soiuz Pisatelei SSSR: Postanovlenie Sekretariata, 1991 Aug. 23 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Annotated photocopy of resolution by the Writer's Union.
  - Pravitel'stvo Moskvy, Tsentral'nyi Okrug, Prefekt, Rasporia zhenie, 1991 Aug. 30 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of decree by the Moscow government.
  - Recognition from Yeltsin, 1993 June - July (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Highlighted copy of decree by President Boris Yeltsin awarding a medal to "Defenders of Free Russia" to Yevtushenko and many others for their actions during the events of 1991 Aug. 19-21, unsigned, 2 p., 1993 June 7; Decree by President Yeltsin awarding the Order of Friendship of Peoples to Yevutshenko, 1 p., 1993 July 16; Signed letter to Yevtushenko congratulating him on his 60th birthday, 1993 July 18. [Last two documents are Yevtushenko's list # 40]
  - O sozdanii muzeia B.L. Pasternaka v poselke "Peredelikino" (About the creation of a Boris Pasternak museum in Peredelikino), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Correspondence concerning the creation of a Pasternak museum in Peredelkino, including a copy of a letter addressed to Gorbachev. Also includes a letter addressed to the Presidium of the Writer's Union, written by Yevtushenko and signed by many writers of the Congress of Writers Union, n.d. [#28 on Yevtushenko's list]
  - Letter from leader of LDPR, Zhirinovsky, V.V., 1993 July 21 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Handwritten and signed card. Yevtushenko's handwritten notes on the back of the envelope describing how he received it. [Yevtushenko's list #42]
    Zhirinovsky, V.
  - Konkretnye predlozheniia v Prezidium Siezda v Redaktsionnuiu Komissiiu (Concrete proposals), undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Manuscript and typescript drafts, one final [?] version signed by Yevtushenko and many others.
  - Speech in Duma, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Mostly manuscript and one typescript drafts.
  - Pochemu v chisle narodnykh deputatov SSSR seichas nuzhny publitsisty masshtaba: by Yevtushenko and V.A. Koroticha, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Typescript.
  - Declaratsiia protiv rasizma, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Manuscripts and annotated typescripts.
  - Suggested Resolutions by PEN - Centres, 1990 May (Box 10, Folder 13)
    On the occasion of the 55th World Congress of International PEN, 1990 May. Manuscripts and annotated typescripts of the "Suggested Resolution from Russian Pen-Centre" concerning the situation in Lithuania. Also includes "Resolution Suggested by the Danish, Finnish, Swedish and Norwegian Centres" expressing concern for the three Baltic countries and the situation in Lithuania, and "Resolution Submitted by the Kurdisch Center" which is concerned with the release of the Turkish scientist, Dr. Ismail Besikci.
  - VII Siezda Pisatelei SSSR, 1981 July 1 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    Invitations.
  - Stenogramma: "YI siezda pisatelei RSFSR", 1985 Dec. 12 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    Poor quality photocopy which includes a speech by Yevtushenko.
  - Ustav Soiuza Rossiskikh Pisatelei (Charter of the Russian Writer's Union), undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
    Photocopy.
  - V Pravlenie Soiuza pisatelei Rossii ot Naimana Anatoliia Genrikhovicha: Zaiavlenie (Declaration), 1992 Feb. 18 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    Letter requesting membership into the Russian Writer's Union, TMsS.
  - Mezhdunarodnyi Kongress Poetov: International Poet Congress, St. Petersburg, 1999 June 3 - 1999 June 6 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    Program.
  - Memorial, 1988 - 1989 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    Annotated typescript, "Soobshchenie dlia pressy" (Information for the press), n.d. Photocopy, "Informatsiia o razvitii dvizheniia 'Memorial'" (Information about the development of the Memorial movement), fragment, n.d. Annotated and signed by Yevtushenko typescript, fragment, n.d. Ticket for "Uchreditel'noi konferentsii vsesoiuznogo dobrovol'nogo istoriko-prosvetitel'skogo obshchestva "Memorial," 1989 Jan 28 - 29. Memorial Manifesto, handout, n.d. Obshchestvennyi Sovet "Memoriala" and Ispolkom "Memoriala," typescript, n.d. Invitation (in French), n.d.
  - Pamiat, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    Postanovlenie Aktiva NPF "Pamiat," photocopy.
  - Kamensk-Ural'skogo soiuza 'tyl-frontu' na 97 god, 1997 Apr. 23 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Soiuz Sovetskikh Pisatelei SSSR: Pasternak, Boris, 1944, 1958 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Lichnaia Kartochka (personal questionaire for the Soviet Writer's Union), original, 1944; handwritten draft of letter to Pasternak from G. Markov, 1 p., 1958 Oct. 24; copy and signed original of typescript of letter from Markov to Pasternak, copy with Pasternak's writing at the bottom, 1 p., 1958 Oct. 24; copy of typescript of letter from Markov to Pasternak, with Pasternak's writing at the bottom, 1 p., 1958 Oct. 26; Handwritten letter [draft?] written by Pasternak addressed to the Presidium of the Soviet Writer's Union, signed, 6 p., 1958 Oct. 27; draft resolution of Writer's Union in which they expel Pasternak, copy of typescript with notes, 2 p., 1958 Oct. 31.
    Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich
  - Soiuz Sovetskikh Pisatelei SSSR: Tvardovskii, Aleksander T., 1943 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    Anketa, filled out in his hand, 1943 Aug. 7.
    Tvardovskii, Aleksander T.
  - Soiuz Sovetskikh Pisatelei SSSR: Zabolotskii, N.A. (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Zaiavlenie from Zabolotskii to the Soviet Writers' Union, copy of typescript with original signature and date, 1 p., 1945 Sept. 4; letter from Saranskii ITL NKVD to Soviet Writers' Union concerning Zabolotskii, copy of typescript with original signatures, 1945 Sept. 6; "Lichnaia Kartochka" filled out by hand, signed, 1948 Mar. 25; Handwritten autobiography, signed, 4 p., 1948 Mar. 25.
    Zabolotskii, Nikolai Alekseevi
  - Soiuz Sovetskikh Pisatelei SSSR: Zoshchenko, M.M., 1943 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    "Lichnaia Kartochka" filled out by hand, signed, 1943 Aug. 3.
    Zoshchenko, M.
  - Soiuz Sovetskikh Pisatelei SSSR: Iz stenogrammy Przidiuma SSP SSSR, 1953 June 23 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    Concerning readmittance to the Soviet Writers' Union, copy of typescript, 7 p., 1953 Aug. June 23.
  - Khar'kov elections: Posters (Box 81, Folder 3)
    Posters with picture of Yevtushenko and the major points of his program. Posters with all of the candidates; one signed by Vladimir Gomozov, another signed by Iurii Titov.
    Titov, Iu.; Gomozov, Vladimir
- Manuscripts, Series 3.
  The Poetry Subseries consists primarily of handwritten drafts of poems at various stages of development. Some poems include typewritten drafts or copies. Notebooks cover the period 1945 to 1997 with some gaps, and consist primarily of handwritten drafts of poems. The Prose Subseries includes drafts and copies of all other types of manuscripts: essays, novels, scripts, screenplays, and speeches.
  - Subseries 1. Poetry
    - Bibliography, 1949 - 1973 (Box 10, Folder 22)
      Typescript of poems by year and typescript entitled "Stikhi, ne vkliuchennye v sbornik poeta" (Poems not included in the poet's collection).
    - Bibliography: Maket Sobraniia Sochinenii Evg. Yevtushenko, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Bibliography: Sostav Knigi, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
      Handwritten list of books of poetry, 4 p., n.d.
    - Bibliography: Ukazatel' neopublikovannykh stikhotvorenii (Index of unpublished poems), undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
      Annotated typescript, 2 p., n.d.
    - Table of Contents for a book of poetry, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      Handwritten by Maria Yevtushenko, 8 p.
    - 1 Maia, undated (Box 10, Folder 27)
      Handwritten, 3 p., n.d.
    - 13, undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
      Handwritten, n.d.
    - 19 avgusta (19 of August), 1991 Aug. 19 (Box 10, Folder 29)
      Handwritten by Maria Yevtushenko, 1 p. Photocopy of handwritten translation into English, 1 p. Typescript of English translation, 1 p.
    - Aldinochka, undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
      Handwritten drafts, 8 p., n.d. Handwritten, English translation, 1 p., n.d.
    - Alla, Drova, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
      Legal pad with drafts of both poems, n.d. Typescript of "Alla", 1 p., n.d.
    - A na komandorakh, undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
      Handwritten drafts, n.d.
    - Avtor stikhotvorenniia "Kommunisty, Vpered!", undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Babii Iar, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 34)
      Handwritten copy, 2 p., 1961 Jun 19. Galley copy, annotations, n.d.
    - Ballada o piati stakanakh, undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
      Two annotated typescripts, 8 p., n.d.
    - Ballada o semge, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Typescript, n.d.
    - Ballada o tvardovskom, 1990 June (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Annotated typescript, 1 p., n.d. Copies of pages from a book, 6 p., 1990 June 8 - 10
    - Barishchl'skaia istoriia, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Handwritten drafts, 6 p., n.d.
    - Bereza, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Typescript with writing on the back, 1 p., n.d.
    - Bezavareini Kapitan, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Handwritten drafts, 9 p., n.d.
    - Bukhta providenie, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Buria, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Annotated typescripts, 5 p., n.d.
    - But' poetom ne samoraskrytie, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Handwritten drafts, 5 p., n.d.
    - Challenger - Requiem, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Handwritten draft (in Russian), 1 p., n.d.
    - Chastushki, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Copy of TMsS, 1 p., n.d.
    - Check point Charly, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Typed and handwritten drafts, 8 p., n.d.
    - Chelovek, prodaiushchii svoe litso, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Handwritten draft, 1 p., n.d.
    - Chelovekofoby, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Handwritten drafts, 2 p., n.d.
    - Chto ia skazhu tebe, Rossiia, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Dai Bog - napisano v kievski gostinitse, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      Handwritten drafts, 14 p., n.d. Typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Dal'niaia Rodstvennitsa, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
      Many handwritten and typed drafts, n.d.
    - Davlenyshi, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      Typescript, 3 p., 1993.
    - Dekabristy/Petrashevtsy, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
      Typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Den' poezii, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Detstvo Pushkina, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Diktatura Kukhariata, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Doch' Aleksandra Aleksandrovicha, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Doch' Komdiva, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
      Handwritten drafts, 8 p., n.d.
    - Dodelka, undated (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Dolgie Provody, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
      Copy of annotated typescript, 1 p., n.d. Typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Dopotopnyi chelovek, 1974 May 20 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      Typescript, 1 p.
    - Dopotopstvo, undated (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Drobitskii Yar, undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Drova, undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
      Handwritten drafts, 3 p., n.d. Includes a hand-drawn map of Zima, 1999 Apr 20. See also "Alla" file for drafts of "Drova".
    - Dvadtsat' pervyi vek, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
      Typescript, 1 p. ( and copy), n.d.
    - Dve liubvi, undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Dve pary lyzh, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Dve snezhinki, undated (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Dvoe, undated (Box 11, Folder 34)
      Handwritten drafts, including some in English, n.d.
    - Epilog, undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
      Typescripts, 3 p., n.d.
    - Ershi, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
      Handwritten draft on cardboard, 1 p., n.d.
    - Eseninu, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 37)
      Typescripts, 2 p., 1965.
    - Eshche ne postavlennie pamiatnika, undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Etazh materinstvo, undated (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Eto ia, Masha, undated (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Evdokiia Lopukhina, undated (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Fuku, undated (Box 11, Folder 42)
      Numerous handwritten drafts, n.d.
    - Gamburg. Panoptikum, undated (Box 11, Folder 43)
      Typescript, 3 p., n.d.
    - Gde doroga domoi?, undated (Box 11, Folder 44)
      Handwritten drafts, 10 p., n.d.
    - Golos, undated (Box 11, Folder 45)
      Handwritten drafts, 7 p., n.d.
    - Gorbachev v Oklakhome, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Gorod Slupov, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Ia druga poterial, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Handwritten draft, 1 p., n.d. Copy of handwritten draft, 1 p., n.d.
    - Ia liubliu tebia bol'she prirody, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Handwritten drafts, 3 p., some in English, n.d.
    - Ia pridu v 21 vek, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
      Handwritten drafts, 22 p., n.d.
    - Izrail' Borisovich Gutchin, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Handwritten drafts, 3 p., n.d.
    - Izrail'skaia Rossia, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Kachka: 1965 Jan. (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Typescript, 1965 Jan.
    - Kazakhstan, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Kazanova: M. Shemiakinu, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Khodiat' sny po Rossii, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Khrap, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)